<document>
	<properties>
		<title>JCS Change Log</title>
		<author email="asmuts@apache.org">Aaron Smuts</author>
	</properties>
	<body>

		<release version="1.2.6.9" date="in CVS">
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update" due-to="">
				The remote cache now sends a byte array to the server instead of the class.  This
				allows you to run the remote server without copies of your objects in its classpath.
				This makes the remote server far easier to use.  
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update" due-to="">
				Created an interface for cache element serializers and made a default
				implementation.  This will allow use to use other serialization mechanisms in 
				the future.  I converted the remote cache to use the standard serializer.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update" due-to="">
				Added several new unit tests.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update" due-to="">
				Improved Javadocs throughout.
			</action>
		</release>
		
		<release version="1.2.6.8" date="in CVS">
			<action dev="asmuts" type="fix" due-to="">
				Moved synchronization from the client to the sorted preferential array.
				This solved the index out of bounds exception that appeared periodically on
				disk cleanup.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update" due-to="">
				Improved Javadocs throughout.
			</action>			
		</release>
				
		<release version="1.2.6.7" date="in CVS">
			<action dev="asmuts" type="fix" due-to="Adam Siefker">
				Fixed shutdown for lateral. Added shutdown observer
				framework. Changed listener thread to a daemon. Made
				executor on listener use a daemon setting thread
				factory.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="fix" due-to="">
				Fixed abstract inner class references for Jikes.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update" due-to="">
				Improved Javadocs throughout.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.2.6.6" date="in CVS">
			<action dev="asmuts" type="fix">
				Properties are loaded using the current thread's
				classloader by default.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="fix">
				When a config file is not found a descriptive error
				message is printed to the logs.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Made an interface for the cache manager to improve
				testability.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Auxiliaries are assigned a cache manager and the lateral
				TCP has a settable source id, so it can be tested.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Increased JGroups version to 2.2.8. It works again. The
				old JGroups didn't work for unknown reasons.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Cleaned up some javadocs.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Improved info level logging for TCP lateral.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Added configuration properties xdocs for TCP lateral,
				indexed disk, and memory cache.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Created concurrent tests for TCP lateral to verify
				correct region behavior.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="update">
				Made BDBJE work with new auxiliary changes.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="fix">
				UDP discovery no longer activates if the lateral type
				isn't TCP.
			</action>
			<action dev="asmuts" type="fix">
				Reduced lateral get timeout to 1 second, rather than 10.
				We still need to disable gets when a timeout occurs.
			</action>
		</release>

	</body>
</document>