<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Using JCS: Some basics for the web</title>
    <author email="ASmuts@yahoo.com">Aaron Smuts</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Using JCS: Some basics for the web">
      <p>
        The primary bottleneck in most dynamic web-based applications is
        the retrieval of data from the database.  While it is relatively
        inexpensive to add more front-end servers to scale the serving
        of pages and images and the processing of content, it is an
        expensive and complex ordeal to scale the database.  By taking
        advantage of data caching, most web applications can reduce
        latency times and scale farther with fewer machines.
      </p>
      <p>
        JCS is a front-tier cache that can be configured to maintain
        consistency across multiple servers by using a centralized
        remote server or by lateral distribution of cache updates.
        Other caches, like the Javlin EJB data cache, are basically
        in-memory databases that sit between your EJB's and your
        database.  Rather than trying to speed up your slow EJB's, you
        can avoid most of the network traffic and the complexity by
        implementing JCS front-tier caching.  Centralize your EJB access
        or your JDBC data access into local managers and perform the
        caching there.
      </p>
      <subsection name="What to cache?">
        <p>
          The data used by most web applications varies in its
          dynamicity, from completely static to always changing at every
          request.  Everything that has some degree of stability can be
          cached.  Prime candidates for caching range from the list data
          for stable dropdowns, user information, discrete and
          infrequently changing information, to stable search results
          that could be sorted in memory.
        </p>
        <p>
          Since JCS is distributed and allows updates and invalidations
          to be broadcast to multiple listeners, frequently changing
          items can be easily cached and kept in sync through your data
          access layer.  For data that must be 100% up to date, say an
          account balance prior to a transfer, the data should directly
          be retrieved from the database.  If your application allows
          for the viewing and editing of data, the data for the view
          pages could be cached, but the edit pages should, in most
          cases, pull the data directly from the database.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="How to cache discrete data">
        <p>
          Let's say that you have an e-commerce book store.  Each book
          has a related set of information that you must present to the
          user.  Let's say that 70% of your hits during a particular day
          are for the same 1,000 popular items that you advertise on key
          pages of your site, but users are still actively browsing your
          catalog of over a million books.  You cannot possibly cache
          your entire database, but you could dramatically decrease the
          load on your database by caching the 1,000 or so most popular
          items.
        </p>
        <p>
          For the sake of simplicity let's ignore tie-ins and
          user-profile based suggestions (also good candidates for
          caching) and focus on the core of the book detail page.
        </p>
        <p>
          A simple way to cache the core book information would be to
          create a value object for book data that contains the
          necessary information to build the display page.  This value
          object could hold data from multiple related tables or book
          subtype table, but lets say that you have a simple table
          called <code>BOOK</code> that looks something like this:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[
  Table BOOK
  BOOK_ID_PK
  TITLE
  AUTHOR
  ISBN
  PRICE
  PUBLISH_DATE
        ]]></source>
        <p>
          We could create a value object for this table called
          <code>BookVObj</code> that has variables with the same
          names as the table columns that might look like this:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[
package com.genericbookstore.data;

import java.io.Serializable;
import java.util.Date;

public class BookVObj implements Serializable
{
    public int bookId = 0;
    public String title;
    public String author;
    public String ISBN;
    public String price;
    public Date publishDate;

    public BookVObj()
    {
    }
}
        ]]></source>
        <p>
          Then we can create a manager called
          <code>BookVObjManager</code> to store and retrieve
          <code>BookVObj</code>'s.  All access to core book data
          should go through this class, including inserts and
          updates, to keep the caching simple.  Let's make
          <code>BookVObjManager</code> a singleton that gets a
          JCS access object in initialization.  The start of the
          class might look like:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[
package com.genericbookstore.data;

import org.apache.commons.jcs.JCS;
// in case we want to set some special behavior
import org.apache.commons.jcs.engine.behavior.IElementAttributes;

public class BookVObjManager
{
    private static BookVObjManager instance;
    private static int checkedOut = 0;
    private static CacheAccess<String, BookVObj> bookCache;

    private BookVObjManager()
    {
        try
        {
            bookCache = JCS.getInstance("bookCache");
        }
        catch (Exception e)
        {
            // Handle cache region initialization failure
        }

        // Do other initialization that may be necessary, such as getting
        // references to any data access classes we may need to populate
        // value objects later
    }

    /**
     * Singleton access point to the manager.
     */
    public static BookVObjManager getInstance()
    {
        synchronized (BookVObjManager.class)
        {
            if (instance == null)
            {
                instance = new BookVObjManager();
            }
        }

        synchronized (instance)
        {
            instance.checkedOut++;
        }

        return instance;
    }
        ]]></source>
        <p>
          To get a <code>BookVObj</code> we will need some access
          methods in the manager. We should be able to get a
          non-cached version if necessary, say before allowing an
          administrator to edit the book data. The methods might
          look like:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[
    /**
     * Retrieves a BookVObj.  Default to look in the cache.
     */
    public BookVObj getBookVObj(int id)
    {
        return getBookVObj(id, true);
    }

    /**
     * Retrieves a BookVObj. Second argument decides whether to look
     * in the cache. Returns a new value object if one can't be
     * loaded from the database. Database cache synchronization is
     * handled by removing cache elements upon modification.
     */
    public BookVObj getBookVObj(int id, boolean fromCache)
    {
        BookVObj vObj = null;

        // First, if requested, attempt to load from cache

        if (fromCache)
        {
            vObj = bookCache.get("BookVObj" + id);
        }

        // Either fromCache was false or the object was not found, so
        // call loadBookVObj to create it

        if (vObj == null)
        {
            vObj = loadvObj(id);
        }

        return  vObj;
    }

    /**
     * Creates a BookVObj based on the id of the BOOK table.  Data
     * access could be direct JDBC, some or mapping tool, or an EJB.
     */
    public BookVObj loadBookVObj(int id)
    {
        BookVObj vObj = new BookVObj();

        vObj.bookID = id;

        try
        {
            boolean found = false;

            // load the data and set the rest of the fields
            // set found to true if it was found

            found = true;

            // cache the value object if found

            if (found)
            {
                // could use the defaults like this
                // bookCache.put( "BookVObj" + id, vObj );
                // or specify special characteristics

                // put to cache

                bookCache.put("BookVObj" + id, vObj);
            }

        }
        catch (Exception e)
        {
            // Handle failure putting object to cache
        }

        return vObj;
    }
        ]]></source>
        <p>
          We will also need a method to insert and update book data.  To
          keep the caching in one place, this should be the primary way
          core book data is created.  The method might look like:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[
    /**
     * Stores BookVObj's in database.  Clears old items and caches
     * new.
     */
    public int storeBookVObj(BookVObj vObj)
    {
        try
        {
            // since any cached data is no longer valid, we should
            // remove the item from the cache if it an update.

            if (vObj.bookID != 0)
            {
                bookCache.remove("BookVObj" + vObj.bookID);
            }

            // put the new object in the cache

            bookCache.put("BookVObj" + id, vObj);
        }
        catch (Exception e)
        {
            // Handle failure removing object or putting object to cache.
        }
    }
}
        ]]></source>
        <p>
          As elements are placed in the cache via <code>put</code>, it
          is possible to specify custom attributes for those elements
          such as its maximum lifetime in the cache, whether or not it
          can be spooled to disk, etc.  It is also possible (and easier)
          to define these attributes in the configuration file as
          demonstrated later.  We now have the basic infrastructure for
          caching the book data.
      </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Selecting the appropriate auxiliary caches">
        <p>
          The first step in creating a cache region is to determine the
          makeup of the memory cache.  For the book store example, I
          would create a region that could store a bit over the minimum
          number I want to have in memory, so the core items always
          readily available.  I would set the maximum memory size to
          <code>1200</code>.  In addition, I might want to have all
          objects in this cache region expire after <code>7200</code>
          seconds.  This can be configured in the element attributes on
          a default or per-region basis as illustrated in the
          configuration file below.
        </p>
        <p>
          For most cache regions you will want to use a disk
          cache if the data takes over about .5 milliseconds to
          create.  The <a href="IndexedDiskAuxCache.html">indexed
          disk cache</a> is the most efficient disk caching
          auxiliary, and for normal usage it is recommended.
        </p>
        <p>
          The next step will be to select an appropriate
          distribution layer.  If you have a back-end server
          running an appserver or scripts or are running multiple
          webserver VMs on one machine, you might want to use
          the centralized <a href="RemoteAuxCache.html">remote
          cache</a>.  The lateral cache would be fine, but since
          the lateral cache binds to a port, you'd have to configure
          each VM's lateral cache to listen to a different port on
          that machine.
        </p>
        <p>
          If your environment is very flat, say a few
          load-balanced webservers and a database machine or one
          webserver with multiple VMs and a database machine,
          then the lateral cache will probably make more sense.
          The <a href="LateralTCPAuxCache.html">TCP lateral
          cache</a> is recommended.
        </p>
        <p>
          For the book store configuration I will set up a region
          for the <code>bookCache</code> that uses the LRU memory
          cache, the indexed disk auxiliary cache, and the remote
          cache.  The configuration file might look like this:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[
# DEFAULT CACHE REGION

# sets the default aux value for any non configured caches
jcs.default=DC,RFailover
jcs.default.cacheattributes=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.engine.CompositeCacheAttributes
jcs.default.cacheattributes.MaxObjects=1000
jcs.default.cacheattributes.MemoryCacheName=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.engine.memory.lru.LRUMemoryCache
jcs.default.elementattributes.IsEternal=false
jcs.default.elementattributes.MaxLife=3600
jcs.default.elementattributes.IdleTime=1800
jcs.default.elementattributes.IsSpool=true
jcs.default.elementattributes.IsRemote=true
jcs.default.elementattributes.IsLateral=true


# CACHE REGIONS AVAILABLE

# Regions preconfigured for caching
jcs.region.bookCache=DC,RFailover
jcs.region.bookCache.cacheattributes=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.engine.CompositeCacheAttributes
jcs.region.bookCache.cacheattributes.MaxObjects=1200
jcs.region.bookCache.cacheattributes.MemoryCacheName=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.engine.memory.lru.LRUMemoryCache
jcs.region.bookCache.elementattributes.IsEternal=false
jcs.region.bookCache.elementattributes.MaxLife=7200
jcs.region.bookCache.elementattributes.IdleTime=1800
jcs.region.bookCache.elementattributes.IsSpool=true
jcs.region.bookCache.elementattributes.IsRemote=true
jcs.region.bookCache.elementattributes.IsLateral=true

# AUXILIARY CACHES AVAILABLE

# Primary Disk Cache -- faster than the rest because of memory key storage
jcs.auxiliary.DC=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.auxiliary.disk.indexed.IndexedDiskCacheFactory
jcs.auxiliary.DC.attributes=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.auxiliary.disk.indexed.IndexedDiskCacheAttributes
jcs.auxiliary.DC.attributes.DiskPath=/usr/opt/bookstore/raf
jcs.auxiliary.DC.attributes.MaxPurgatorySize=10000
jcs.auxiliary.DC.attributes.MaxKeySize=10000
jcs.auxiliary.DC.attributes.OptimizeAtRemoveCount=300000

# Remote RMI Cache set up to failover
jcs.auxiliary.RFailover=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.auxiliary.remote.RemoteCacheFactory
jcs.auxiliary.RFailover.attributes=
    org.apache.commons.jcs.auxiliary.remote.RemoteCacheAttributes
jcs.auxiliary.RFailover.attributes.RemoteTypeName=LOCAL
jcs.auxiliary.RFailover.attributes.FailoverServers=scriptserver:1102
jcs.auxiliary.RFailover.attributes.GetOnly=false
        ]]></source>
        <p>
          I've set up the default cache settings in the above
          file to approximate the <code>bookCache</code>
          settings.  Other non-preconfigured cache regions will
          use the default settings.  You only have to configure
          the auxiliary caches once.  For most caches you will
          not need to pre-configure your regions unless the size
          of the elements varies radically.  We could easily put
          several hundred thousand <code>BookVObj</code>'s in
          memory.  The <code>1200</code> limit was very
          conservative and would be more appropriate for a large
          data structure.
        </p>
        <p>
          To get running with the book store example, I will also
          need to start up the remote cache server on the
          scriptserver machine.  The
          <a href="RemoteAuxCache.html">remote cache
          documentation</a> describes the configuration.
        </p>
        <p>
          I now have a basic caching system implemented for my book
          data.  Performance should improve immediately.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>



